地         球         脉         动   I I
画 外 音
大卫 · 爱登堡   爵士
在过去的六千年
In the last 6,000 years
地球的表面发生了突然的变化
the surface of our planet has undergone a sudden change.
一个新的栖息地已经出现
A new habitat has appeared,
完全人为设计和建造的这个景观
entirely designed and constructed by one species for its own purpose.
也许会对动物的生命造成威胁
This man-made landscape may seem alien to animal life
但对于勇者来说  这是一个充满奇妙机遇的世界
but for the bold, this is a world of surprising opportunity.
城        市
印度焦特布尔市
Jodhpur, India.
一群单身的雄性长尾叶猴
A gang of bachelor male langurs
前来挑战这块领地的雄性首领
has come to challenge the resident alpha male.
他统治着这片珍贵的城市领土
This alpha rules over a valuable urban territory.
但维护权威是一场长期的斗争
But maintaining dominance here is a constant struggle.
单身雄猴们联合起来试图推翻猴王
The bachelors have united to try and overthrow him.
如果他们胜利了  其中一位挑战者
If they win, one of the challengers
将继承猴王的后宫
will take over the alpha's troop of females,
并杀死他的幼崽
and may kill his infants.
这个单身猴群里有十五只公猴
There are 15 males in this bachelor group.
猴王必须把他们全部逐出自己的领地
The alpha must evict every single one of them from his territory.
他已经赶走了半数挑战者
He has chased half the bachelors away,
但有一支小分队折了回来
but a splinter group has looped back
正在骚扰他的母猴们
and is harassing his females.
他不得不再次加入战斗
Once again, he has to battle.
终于赶走了所有来犯者
Finally, he manages to expel them all.
他凯旋而归
He returns home victorious,
但右腿受了重伤
but with a serious wound on his right leg.
对他而言  城市生活布满荆棘
It's a hard life for him in the city.
每天都上演着入侵驱逐战
Keeping the intruders away is a daily challenge.
但一切都值得
But it's worth it.
对长尾叶猴来说
For these urban territories
这边城区也许是世上最优良的栖息地
are probably the best langur territories in the world.
因为遍地都是觅食场
They're filled with rich feeding grounds.
在这些寺院花园中
Here in the temple gardens,
几百年来  长尾叶猴与人类建立了一种奇妙的关系
the langurs have, over centuries, developed a surprising relationship.
这层关系为猴群提供了源源不断的食物
One that guarantee's them a constantly replenished source of food.
当地人将长尾叶猴视为印度教中猴神哈奴曼的化身
The people here associate langurs with the Hindu God, Lord Hanuman,
对他们毕恭毕敬
and revere them.
珍馐佳肴  应有尽有
They're given all the food they can eat.
优质饮食带来了生育高峰
And this high-energy diet has led to a baby boom.
城市里雌性长尾叶猴的生育率
Female langurs in this city
是森林中同类的两倍
give birth to twice as many young as their forest counterparts.
这只母猴伙食很好  奶水充足到
This mother is so well fed that her rich milk
能养育起野外极其罕见的小生命
can support something rarely seen in the wild.
双胞胎
Twins.
这些幼崽聚集成群
And all these babies can create troops
队伍比周边森林里的要大得多
that are far larger than those found in the forests nearby.
觅食时间缩短  使得他们有更多时间可以玩耍
With less time spent looking for food,there is more time for play.
生活在城市中好处良多
The rewards of living in a city can be huge.
难的是如何寻找自己的一席之地
The challenge is to find your niche.
这样一个世界  并不是专为野生动物的
But how to create a home in a world that wasn't designed for wildlife?
灯光  声音和忙碌超过任何地方的自然世界
It's far brighter, louder and busier than anywhere in the natural world.
持续的交通造成了动物运动的障碍
The continuous traffic creates barriers to animal movement.
今后十年  城市面积预计将
And in this decade,the urban environment
扩张约百分之三十
is predicted to grow by nearly 30%.
更重要的是  来这里的
What's more, to come here,
动物必须与世界顶级捕食者竞争
animals have to compete with the world's top predator.
人们建立了这里的规则
People makes the rules here.
四十亿人口现在居住在城市环境中
Four billion human beings now live in the urban environment.
在这里  动物必须抗争最大的变化
It's here that animals have to contend with the greatest change
发生在我们的星球
that is happenning to the face our planet.
所以为什么会有动物想来这里呢
So why would any animal want to come here?
纽约市
New York City.
这座高楼林立的城市  与地球上许多地方一样远离自然
This densely built-up landscape is as unnatural as anywhere on Earth.
而这只游隼正站在高处  俯瞰这座城市
And yet this wild peregrine falcon looks out onto an ideal habitat.
奇怪的是  这片变化巨大的土地
Strange as it may seem, this vastly-altered landscape
竟然重现了游隼进化的生境
replicates the conditions in which peregrines evolved.
高耸的建筑上面有许多平台
The towering buildings have a multitude of ledges
可供游隼筑巢
on which falcons can nest
鸟巢高度也足够他们乘风飞翔
and the high perches that they need to catch the wind.
纽约市的游隼密度
New York City has the highest density
居世界之最
of nesting peregrines anywhere on the planet.
风被摩天大楼阻挡后会向上偏转
Winds striking the sides of the skyscrapers
有利于游隼飞得更高
are deflected upwards and can help the birds gain height.
烈日下大面积的混凝土散发的热量形成上升热气流
And the great areas of concrete roasting in the sun create thermals,
游隼不费吹灰之力便可以在城市上空翱翔
so that, with very little effort， the birds can soar over the city.
不计其数的游隼定居于此
And so many peregrines can live here,
是因为城市近地面生活着许多猎物
because down at street level, there is a lot of potential prey.
游隼俯冲时的飞行时速
Diving from height, the falcons can reach speeds
超过时速三百二十二公里
of over 200 miles an hour.
但猎物躲在低处  离建筑物很近
But their prey stay down low and close to the buildings.
风险太大了
Too risky.
它停止了俯冲
The peregrine pulls out of his stoop.
但辛苦不会白费
But the effort is not wasted.
游隼需要将猎物驱赶到开阔地带
The falcons need to flush their prey into the open.
曼哈顿四面环水
And Manhattan is surrounded by water.
出城后便可谓胜券在握
Out here the odds change.
正中游隼下怀
And in the peregrine's favour.
一年到头都有着丰富的食物
With abundant prey here all year round,
仅用了四十年
it has taken only 40 years
游隼在此建立栖息地
for these falcons to establish themselves here.
穿梭在摩登大厦中
And now, among skyscrapers, they're more successful
与旷野中的同类相比  它们更胜一筹
than their cousins living in the wilderness.
印度孟买人口超过两千万
Mumbai, in India, is home to over 20 million people..
也生存着许多猎食者
And there are predators here
尽管难得一见  也着实令人胆战心惊
that, though rarely seen, are rightly feared.
食肉动物们
Carnivores,
正向着毫无戒心的猎物
lured by the prospect of plentiful unsuspecting prey
一步步靠近
are on the prowl.
一只金钱豹
A leopard.
在夜色的掩护下  他们每晚都会出来猎食
Every night, under the cover of darkness they come out to hunt.
大型食肉动物需要
These are big animals,
寻找大型猎物才能充饥
and they're looking for large prey to satisfy their hunger.
为了多捕捉一些画面揭示他们的猎食行为
To catch more than a glimpse of them and reveal their hunting behaviour,
我们需要夜视摄像机
you need night-vision cameras.
在过去的二十五年里
Leopards have attacked almost 200 people here
金钱豹袭击过约两百个人
in the last 25 years.
但人类并不是他们日常的捕食对象
But humans are not their usual prey.
这些金钱豹在寻找其他猎物
These leopards are on the hunt for something else.
猪
Pigs.
他们更喜欢人类圈养在城市里
These leopards prefer to hunt the domestic animals
数量可观的家畜
that people have brought to the city in considerable numbers.
猪喜欢群居
The pigs keep their family close.
城市里无休止的嘈杂为金钱豹提供了便利
The ceaseless noise of the city plays to their advantage.
掩盖了他们的脚步
It conceals their approach.
金钱豹利用掩护能在全城各地捕猎
And the leopards are using this cover to hunt all over the city.
这个种群日益繁荣
This is a thriving population.
事实上  世界上金钱豹数量最多的地方
In fact, the highest concentration of leopards in the world
就是这里
is right here.
充足的食物并不是吸引野生动物迁入城市的唯一要素
It's not only the abundance of food that attracts wild animals to cities.
城市的气温通常比郊外略高几度
They're usually several degrees warmer than the surrounding countryside.
十二月的罗马
And here in Rome, in Decembe
有一种动物充分利用着这丝温暖
one animal is taking full advantage of this extra heat.
在城市中留下自己的印记
And it's leaving it's mark.
冬季的每一天
In a single winter's day,
都有十吨粪便雨降临这座城市
ten tonnes of its droppings rain down on the city.
欧椋鸟
Starlings.
夜晚  它们在郊外摄食后
In the evening, they come back to the warmth of the city
返回温暖的城市
after feeding in the neighbouring countryside.
它们必须返回栖息地
They must return to their roosting trees.
但第一个回来的最有可能
But the first to do so are at the highest risk
被猛禽袭击
of being caught by birds of prey.
所以它们等候大部队一同抵达
So, they wait for others to arrive.
数量越多就越安全
There's safety in numbers.
天光渐暗  城市上空被数百万只欧椋鸟占据
As daylight fades, the sky fills with a staggering one million starlings.
上演一场蔚然壮观的自然演出
And then follows one of nature's great spectaculars.
它们是如何  又是为何成群起舞
How, or indeed why, they perform these marvellous aerobatics,
至今我们还无法完全理解
we still do not fully understand.
最终  它们会成群结队地降落
Eventually, en masse，they brave the descent
挑选最喜欢的树枝落脚
and fill the branches of their favourite trees.
在这样寒冷的冬夜里
On these cold winter nights, the city's extra warmth
城市的温暖可能事关生死存亡
can mean the difference between life and death.
城市不仅能提供大量食物与庇护所
A city, of course, can provide
还有许多宝藏
not only shelter and abundant food, but glamour.
这些精心挑选的小物件
These varied objects have been carefully chosen
颜色鲜艳  溢彩流光
by a bird for their brightness and their colour.
这只园丁鸟花了十余年时间
This great bowerbird has spent over a decade
收集了这些物品  其中大部分是人造装饰
building this collection of mostly man-made objects.
澳大利亚汤斯维尔市的高尔夫球场上
Out on a golf course in Townsville, Australia,
他正在为这座巨型凉亭做最后的修饰
he's putting the final touches to his enormous bower,
争取能够博得来访雌鸟的青睐
that he hopes will impress a visiting female.
他每天都会花两小时来调整装饰物的布局
He spends two hours each day rearranging his prized objects.
“放在那边可能更好看一点”
"Perhaps that would look a little better over there."
可似乎还是差了点什么
But it seems that something is missing.
他没有进城去找新装饰
Instead of going into town to collect new objects,
而是决定抢劫邻居
he's decided to raid his neighbour's bower.
“晾衣夹  太棒了”
"A clothes peg! Excellent!"
“还有一辆闪亮的玩具车”
"And a shiny toy car."
如果被发现就不好玩了
It's a risky game if you get caught.
主人回来了
The owner is back.
有一座凉亭  值得去冒险
There is one bower where the risk is worth it.
一件特别的物品吸引了他的目光
A particular object has caught his eye.
他需要等主人离开
He'll have to wait for the owner to leave.
机会来了
This is his chance.
这是真正的宝贝
A real treasure.
深红色的心
A scarlet heart.
“拿到了”
"Got it."
供雌鸟参观的舞台已经准备就绪
The stage is now set for female visitors.
他似乎很走运
His luck may be in.
可以开始尽情引诱了
The seduction can now begin.
他开始炫耀自己的收藏
He's showing off his best goods.
“这个塑料管怎么样”
"Perhaps a little plastic piping?
“我还有鲜艳的红丝线”
"Or maybe a bit of coloured string?"
但这位访客似乎对此毫无兴趣
But his guest doesn't seem to be paying much attention.
“这把叉子呢”
"A fork?
“女士”
"Madame?"
对方依旧无动于衷
Nothing seems to be working.
事情有些不对劲
Something is just not quite right here.
但他还有一招
But he still has one trick up his sleeve.
那颗红心
The scarlet heart.
作为压轴节目  他张开了头部后
As a final thrill，he expands the pink crest
头部后侧的粉色羽冠
on the back of his head.
证明他已经成年
The sign of his adulthood.
但他弄错了
But he's made a mistake.
这只不是雌鸟
This is not a female
而是一只还没有长出羽冠的雄鸟
but a young male who hasn't yet developed that head crest.
他衔起红心飞走了
And he's making off with the scarlet heart.
在城里求偶着实不易
It's not easy finding sex in the city.
在城市里养活子女也不轻松
Raising a family in the city is not easy either.
多伦多已经到了春季
It's spring time in Toronto,
这只浣熊妈妈的家  从树顶换成了屋顶
and this mother raccoon has exchanged her native treetops for rooftops.
两个月前她产下的幼崽
Since giving birth two months ago,
被她放在烟囱里  那里温暖又安全
she's kept her offspring safe and warm inside a chimney.
现在  这些宝宝们住不下了
Now, her young have outgrown their nursery.
这是当妈妈的第一个大挑战
This is her first major challenge as a mother.
搬新家
The time has come to move to a new home.
她得把孩子们从屋顶带下来
She needs to get her youngster to ground level.
可脚下不是方便攀爬的树干
But instead of an easy climb down a tree,
而是垂直陡峭的墙壁
she is faced with a vertical drop,
几乎没有着力点
with little to cling onto.
浣熊宝宝第一次看到城市世界
Her baby's first glimpse of the urban world,
却是在惊悚的九米高空
from a terrifying 30 feet up.
这只浣熊宝宝是最后一个了
This is the last of her litter to be brought down.
它的兄弟们
Its siblings are already
已经忙着探索未知世界
busy exploring the area.
他们要学的还有许多
And they have much to learn.
这只浣熊宝宝掉进后巷  被困在了这里
This one has fallen into a back alley and is trapped.
妈妈来救它  告诉它应该怎么做
Mother comes to the rescue and demonstrates what must be done.
就是这样
That's the way.
浣熊是一群投机分子
Raccoons are opportunists.
十分渴望探索新世界
And they're eager to explore.
他们需要尽快学会
But they'll have to learn very quickly
如何适应这样一个既陌生
how to get along in this strange new environment
又充满危险的世界
so full of hazards.
妈妈再次前来救助
Mother comes to the rescue once more.
城市浣熊与乡村浣熊相比
Urban raccoons are now demonstrably better
拥有更加卓越的问题解决能力
at problem-solving than their country cousins.
食物来源如此丰富
When the feeding opportunities are this good,
花点时间想办法获取食物
the time spent working out how to get to it
也非常值得
is well worth it.
复杂的城市生活
The complexity of urban life
需要智取
favours the clever.
但是要想在白天与人类竞争
But to compete with humanity during daylight hours,
需要的不只是智慧
takes more than just intelligence.
还有胆量
It takes nerve.
一群雄心勃勃的猴子
One enterprising species of monkey
搬到了印度斋浦尔市
has moved into the city of Jaipur in India.
恒河猕猴
The Rhesus macaque.
如何拿到这些鲜嫩多汁的水果呢
But how to get a share of all this juicy fruit?
每天早上  猴子军团都会和上班族一样
Every morning, the troop make the same journey
走同样的路线  穿越城市丛林
through the urban jungle, just as human commuters do.
有时候  难免会遇到交通拥堵
Sometimes, inevitably, there are traffic jams.
等他们抵达市场  麻烦就开始了
Once they get to the market, trouble begins.
有勇有谋
Being both intelligent and brazen
才能在人类的地盘占上风
is the key to beating human beings on their home turf.
简直是光天化日下的抢劫
It's daylight robbery.
在大多数人看来  生活在城市中的
There are some animals that most would consider too dangerous
有些动物太过危险
to tolerate in the city.
斑鬣狗
Spotted hyenas.
它们所到之处  其他动物都退避三舍
They're feared throughout their range.
在埃塞俄比亚哈拉市郊外
In the outskirts of Hara in Ethiopia,
两群鬣狗针锋相对  准备争夺宝贵资源
two clans are coming face to face to battle over a prized resource.
两边队伍各有六十只左右
There are about 60 hyenas in each clan.
势均力敌
And they're well matched.
经过三小时的来回周旋
After three hours of posturing back and forth,
一支队伍败退
the losers retreat
赢家则出发去享受战果
and the victors head to claim their prize.
它们争夺的正是进入城区的权利
They have been fighting over access to the city.
一旦穿过城墙  它们就直奔目的地
Once inside the city walls，they head for one place.
而且也很清楚该如何去那里
And they know exactly how to get there.
一家历史悠久的肉店
The ancient meat market.
动物残骸的浓重气息飘散在空气中
The scent of all these carcasses lies heavy in the air.
这个传统已经持续了四百多年
This tradition goes back over 400 years.
屠夫们会把不要的骨头扔出来
The human butchers put out the bones they don't need
由这些鬣狗负责处理
and these hyenas deal with them.
只有它们有这个能力
They're the only animals that can.
其他动物的咬合力不足以咬断骨头
No other here has such powerful bone-crushing jaws.
人类与野兽的这种关系
And this relationship between man and beast
如今已经发展到了新高度
has now been taken a step further.
约瑟夫在呼唤鬣狗们去他家
Yousuf is calling the hyenas to his house.
他和他的祖辈  连续五代人
He and his forefathers, going back five generations,
在喂食这些鬣狗时
have been feeding the hyenas
都直接用手
by hand.
住在这里的市民们认为
The inhabitants of this town believe that hyenas
鬣狗还有一个非常重要的本事
provide another very important service.
能够吞噬游荡在街道上的恶魂
Eating the bad spirits that haunt the streets.
这种动物凶猛而残暴
These are wild and ferocious animals,
但是在城区内
but once within these city walls,
他们表现出了完全不同的一面
they behave in a completely different way.
在非洲的其他地区  大家都十分惧怕斑鬣狗
Throughout the rest of Africa，spotted hyenas are feared
因为它们猎食家畜  甚至伤及孩童
because they kill livestock, sometimes even children.
斑鬣狗大概是地球上最受诟病的动物
They are perhaps the most vilified animal on our planet.
然而  在哈勒尔
However, here in Harar,
他们却能够与人类和平共处
their relationship with people is entirely peaceful.
赢得了人类的信任
They have won the trust of man.
丧失对人类的恐惧
Losing its fear of humans
让一种动物遍布世界各个城市
has enabled one animal to spread into cities everywhere,
而且数量庞大
and in huge numbers.
鸽子是目前最成功的城市鸟类
Pigeons are by far the most successful urban bird.
在法国南部的阿尔比
Here, in Albi, in the south of France,
鸽群飞到河边沐浴
the pigeons come to the river to bathe.
它们要整理飞羽
They need to preen their flight feathers,
清洗掉城市的灰尘
clean off the city dust,
并给自己降降温
and cool themselves down.
而死神正埋伏以待
But death lies in wait.
捕食者正是利用了
A predator that has taken advantage
鸽子在城市得以成功生存的法宝
of the very thing that has led to the pigeon's success...
它们已丧失的恐惧感
Their lack of fear.
鸽子洗澡时  羽毛上的油脂顺流而下
As the pigeons bathe，oil from their plumage flows downstream,
被捕食者察觉
and is detected.
一条巨大的六须鲶鱼
A monstrous Wels catfish.
虽然才被引入此地四十年
Introduced here just 40 years ago,
繁殖数量却已大大增长  几乎迫使本地鱼类灭绝
they have proliferated. Virtually exterminated the local fish stocks...
现在它们将猎食对象转向了鸽子
And they've now developed a taste for pigeon.
由于视力微弱
Their eyesight is poor,
它们依靠触须来探测猎物的动静
so they use their barbels to sense the movements of their victims.
对底栖鱼类来说
This is a radical new hunting strategy
这是种全新的捕猎策略
for what is normally a bottom-dwelling fish.
在城市居住了上千年之后
After a thousand years of living in this city,
鸽子现在却要学会避开水里的鱼
pigeons are now having to learn to avoid a fish
我们的城市在不断变化
Our cities are always changing.
有时极为迅速
Sometimes very swiftly.
动物们必须应对这些改变
And animals must cope with the changes,
否则就会消失
or disappear.
近年来  最大的变化之一
One of the greatest changes in recent times
是由一项历史还不到一百四十年的发明引起的
has come from a single invention made less than 140 years ago.
电灯
Electric light.
它的影响力越来越大
It has become more and more powerful,
点亮了我们的街道
filling our streets with light.
城市灯光无处不在
It's everywhere in the city.
甚至延伸到地下
It even goes under ground.
白天与黑夜的区别愈发难以分辨
The difference between day and night is becoming less and less perceptible.
这对野生动物产生了深远的影响
And that has a profound effect on the activities of wildlife.
在野外  光引发动物的各种行为
In the wilderness, light triggers all kinds of behaviour.
在月圆之夜
On the night of the full moon,
数百只刚孵化的小玳瑁
hundreds of tiny hawksbill turtle hatchlings
从安全的沙底洞穴中钻出
emerge from the safety of their nest deep in the sand.
本能驱使它们尽快爬到海里
Their instinct is to reach the sea as quickly as possible.
指引它们方向的是海水倒映的月光
And their guide is the light of the full moon reflected on the water.
但这只小玳瑁感到很困惑
But this young hatchling is confused.
它正朝错误的方向爬去
It's going in the wrong direction.
明亮的灯光从陆地照来
Bright light is coming from the land.
让这些小玳瑁都从沙滩爬向内陆
And all these hatchlings are travelling up the beach towards it.
捕食者伺机而动
Predators are ready to take advantage.
螃蟹将巢穴直接建在沙滩灯光下
Crabs now make their burrows directly beneath the beach lights
等猎物自己送上门
and wait for their prey to come to them.
即使能成功逃脱
Even if a hatchling escapes,
它们仍身处险境
they're still in peril.
灯光愈发具有迷惑性
The lights become more and more bewildering.
这片沙滩上百分之八十的小玳瑁
80% of all hatchlings on this beach
都因城市的灯光而迷失了方向
are now disorientated by the lights of the town.
许多小生命终结了在马路上
Roads bring many to their end.
每晚都有数百只小玳瑁被困在下水道
Hundreds get trapped in storm drains every night.
在陆地上的长途跋涉使它筋疲力尽
Exhausted by the effort of travelling such a distance on land,
这只小玳瑁很可能活不过今晚
this hatchling's chances of surviving the night are slim.
这只玳瑁只是无数
This turtle is one of the countless species
无法适应城市
that have been unable to adapt to the change
环境变化的物种之一
brought about by the urban environment.
只有少数动物
Only a small number of animals
找到了与人类共存的方法
have managed to find ways of living alongside us.
每隔十年  就有英国面积大小的区域
And every 10 years, an area the size of Britain
被水泥森林吞噬
disappears under a jungle of concrete.
但一切并非只能如此
But it doesn't have to be like this.
难道我们不能建造更加融合自然的城市吗
Could it not be possible to build cities more in harmony with nature?
我们是这个环境的设计师
We are the designers of this enviroment.
是否邀请野生动物回归城市  方式如何  都取决于我们
How, and whether we decide to invite the wildlife back, is up to us.
这棵树被吊到约三十层楼高
This tree is rising nearly 30 storeys.
它和其他近八百棵树一起被种下 旨在打造一座米兰的垂直森林
It's one of almost 800 being planted to create a vertical forest in Milan.
这个数量的树木  相当于两公顷的森林
This number of living trees would normally fill two hectares of woodland,
可在这里  它们只占据了十分之一的面积
but here, they occupy one-tenth of that area.
绿化建筑的外墙和屋顶
Greening the walls and roofs of our buildings
就能打造一座茂盛而广阔的栖息地
could create a rich and extensive habitat,
只要我们有心去做
if we wanted it to do so.
有一座城市  正在大规模实践这个构想
There is one city where that idea is being applied on a major scale.
新加坡
Singapore.
这座城市在四十五年里共种了两百万棵树
Two million trees have been planted here in the last 45 years.
如今  它成为了世界上物种最丰富的城市
This city is now richer in species than any other in the world.
构建自然城市的实践延伸至城市的每个角落
And this practise extends to all parts of the city.
城市中的航道被清理干净
The waterways have been cleaned up,
江獭们得以重新回归
and smooth-coated otters are coming back.
不过  城市绿化最壮观的例子
But perhaps, the most spectacular example of city greening
也许是这片超级树林
is this grove of super trees.
这些四十五米高的金属建筑现在充满了生机
These 150 feet high metal structures are now full of life.
分枝上种植了匍匐植物  蔓延生长
Creepers have been planted to grow over the outermost branches.
这是否就是我们未来的城市景观呢
Is this a vision of our cities of the future?
也许某天  我们会看到更多的野生动物
The potential to see animals thriving within our cities
在全世界的城市的里繁衍生息的景象
is achievable across the globe.
如今半数以上的人口生活在城市中
More than half of us now live in an urban environment.
我们是否愿意打造美好的地球家园
Whether we choose to create a home for others too
不仅是为了人类
is up to us.